Guide to the Myres Smith McDougal Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Myres Smith McDougal papers
1929-1999
MS 1636
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
164.67
(159 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, audio cassettes, and videotapes of conversations between Myres S. McDougal and colleagues.
McDougal, Myres S. (Myres Smith), 1906-1998
Conditions Governing Access
Accessions 1995-M-002, 1995-M-082, 1995-M-212, 1996-M-031,1997-M-118, 1998-M-114, and 1999-M-056 unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu. The request should outline the scope and purpose of the research project, why the researcher believes the material is relevant to their project, and contact information. If possible the request should also include a list of specific material of interest including collection, box, and folder numbers (or folder descriptions if folders are not numbered). The review may take several weeks.
All other material is open to research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Myres S. McDougal, 1992-1995, and 1997-1998; and transfer from the Yale Law School, 1998-1999.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, audio cassettes, and videotapes of conversations between Myres S. McDougal and colleagues.
General
39 photographs in 1995-M-002, box twelve and 1999-M-056, box 2 reported missing in 2014.
Law; Lawyers; McDougal, Myres S. (Myres Smith), 1906-1998
- Inventory
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Videotaped discussions
    - Tipson, Frederick, 1992 September 11 (Box 1–2)
    - Willard, Andrew, 1992 September 11 (Box 3)
    - deB Katzenbach, Nicholas, 1992 October 3 (Box 4)
    - Schwebel, Stephen, 1992 November 6 (Box 5)
    - Rostow, Eugene V., 1992 December 11 (Box 6)
    - Feliciano, Florentino, 1993 January 7 (Box 7)
    - Johnstone, Quintin, 1993 February 1 (Box 8–9)
    - Gardner, Richard, 1993 February 15 (Box 10)
    - Olmstead, Cecil, 1993 March 1 (Box 11)
    - Higgins, Rosalyn, 1993 March 27 (Box 12)
    - Clark, Elias, 1993 May 14 (Box 13)
- Additional Material, 1962-1988; Accession 1994-M-059; 12.5 linear feet (10 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Additional inventory by Nancy Lyon and Carol King 1994 Feb
  Received from: Myres S. McDougal 1994 Jan 7
  - A, 1969-1980 (Box 1)
  - American Bar Association, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Arens, Richard, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Ba, 1970-1981 (Box 1)
  - Basit, Abdul, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Baxter, Richard, 1970-1980 (Box 1)
  - Be, 1967-1981 (Box 1)
  - Bf-Bv, 1973-1981 (Box 1)
  - Bri, 1970-1981 (Box 1)
  - Ca, 1970-1980 (Box 1)
  - Cabranes, Jose, 1970-1980 (Box 1)
  - Caldwell, Mary Ellen, 1970-1981 (Box 1)
  - Ce, 1967-1980 (Box 1)
  - Ch, 1969-1981 (Box 1)
  - Committee on International Exchange of Persons, 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Consortium for World Order Studies, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Coq-, 1970-1981 (Box 2)
  - Da, 1970-1981 (Box 2)
  - Deak, Francis, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Di-, 1970-1979 (Box 2)
  - E, 1970-1980 (Box 2)
  - F, 1971-1981 (Box 2)
  - Foster, Philip, 1975-1984 (Box 2)
  - Fund For Peace, 1972-1977 (Box 2)
  - Ga-Ge, 1970-1980 (Box 2)
  - Gi-Go, 1971-1981 (Box 2)
  - Gr-, 1971-1978 (Box 2)
  - H, 1970-1978 (Box 2)
  - Handl, Gunther, 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - He, 1970-1981 (Box 2)
  - Higgins, Rosalyn, and Terrence, 1970-1980 (Box 2)
  - Ho-Hz, 1970-1981 (Box 3)
  - I, 1971-1981 (Box 3)
  - Ingber, Stanley, 1971-1981 (Box 3)
  - J, 1970-1980 (Box 3)
  - Ka-Kh, 1971-1984 (Box 3)
  - Ki-, 1970-1981 (Box 3)
  - Kim, Suk Jo, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - La, 1971-1980 (Box 3)
  - Law School administration, 1970-1977 (Box 3)
  - Le, 1970-1980 (Box 3)
  - Le-, 1970-1981 (Box 3)
  - Libonati, Michael, 1967-1981 (Box 3)
  - Ma, 1971-1981 (Box 3)
  - Maunk, Maunk, 1962-1971 (Box 3)
  - Mc, 1967-1981 (Box 4)
  - McLean, George, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Me-Mi, 1970-1980 (Box 4)
  - Mo, 1971-1981 (Box 4)
  - Mohammad, Noor, 1961-1979 (Box 4)
  - Moore, John Norton, 1969-1981 (Box 4)
  - Murty, B.S., 1972-1980 (Box 4)
  - Na, 1969-1978 (Box 4)
  - Nayak, K.N., 1969-1978 (Box 4)
  - Nagan, Winston, 1973-1979 (Box 4)
  - Nathan, Harold S., 1972-1980
  - Ne-Nz, 1970-1981 (Box 4)
  - New York Law School, Nunes, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
  - Pa-Ph, 1971-1980 (Box 4)
  - Pi-Pz, 1970-1983 (Box 5)
  - Policy Sciences, 1974-1981 (Box 5)
  - Q, 1970-1978 (Box 5)
  - Ra-Re, 1971-1981 (Box 5)
  - Raman, K.V., 1970-1979 (Box 5)
  - Rao, P. Sreenivasa, 1969-1978 (Box 5)
  - Reisman, 1969-1977 (Box 5)
  - Rh-Ri, 1968-1978 (Box 5)
  - Ro-, 1971-1980 (Box 5)
  - Rostow/ Rotival, 1967-1981 (Box 5)
  - Ru-, 1971-1980 (Box 5)
  - Ryu, Helen and Paul, 1970-1980 (Box 5)
  - Sa-Sc, 1971-1980 (Box 5)
  - Sch, 1971-1980 (Box 5)
  - Schneider, Jan, 1971-1980 (Box 5)
  - Se-Sh, 1971-1980 (Box 5)
  - si-sn, 1970-1980 (Box 5)
  - Spain Robert S., 1968-1974 (Box 5)
  - So-Std, 1968-1978 (Box 5)
  - Spencer, John H., 1970-1975 (Box 5)
  - Ste-, 1970-1980 (Box 5)
  - Stu-, 1970-1980 (Box 5)
  - Suzuki, Eisuke, 1973-1981 (Box 6)
  - Ta-Ti, 1971-1981 (Box 6)
  - Thigpen, Richard, 1970-1978 (Box 6)
  - Tj-Tz, 1969-1978 (Box 6)
  - U, 1970-1979 (Box 6)
  - V, 1971-1983 (Box 6)
  - Veblen, John E, 1971-1973 (Box 6)
  - Wa-Wh, 1971-1981 (Box 6)
  - Wang, Alferd, 1965-1981 (Box 6)
  - Weston, Burns, 1963-1979 (Box 6)
  - Weyrauch, Walter, 1964-1978 (Box 6)
  - Wheeler, John, 1973-1980 (Box 6)
  - Wi-Wz, 1970-1980 (Box 6)
  - Wiernert, John W., 1970-1978 (Box 6)
  - Wolfe, Gary, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
  - Wolff, Morris, 1969-1981 (Box 6)
  - Y, 1970-1979 (Box 6)
  - Z, 1970-1980 (Box 6)
  - A, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - B, 1982 (Box 7)
  - C, 1982 (Box 7)
  - D-E, 1982 (Box 7)
  - F-G, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - H, 1977-1982 (Box 7)
  - Hudson Medical Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - I, J, K, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - L, 1982 (Box 7)
  - M, 1978-1982 (Box 7)
  - N, 1982 (Box 7)
  - O (2 folders), 1972-1982 (Box 7)
  - P, Q, R, 1980-1982 (Box 7)
  - S, 1973-1982 (Box 7)
  - T, U, V, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - X, Y, Z, 1982 (Box 7)
  - A, 1981-1987 (Box 8)
  - Arsanjani, Mahnoush, 1976-1987 (Box 8)
  - Ba-Be, 1984-1987 (Box 8)
  - Be-Bz, 1985-1987 (Box 8)
  - C, 1983-1987 (Box 8)
  - Ch-, 1983-1987 (Box 8)
  - D, 1983-1987 (Box 8)
  - E, 1983-1987 (Box 8)
  - Exams, 1982 (Box 8)
  - Fa-Fn, 1983-1987 (Box 8)
  - Fortas, Abe, 1970-1983 (Box 8)
  - G, 1966-1987 (Box 8)
  - Garrison, Peter, 1983-1987 (Box 8)
  - H, 1982-1987 (Box 8)
  - I, 1983-1987 (Box 9)
  - J, 1969-1987 (Box 9)
  - K, 1982-1987 (Box 9)
  - L, (2 folders), 1981-1987 (Box 9)
  - Lasswell, Harold, 1980-1987 (Box 9)
  - M- (2 folders), 1983-1987 (Box 9)
  - Mc, 1982-1988 (Box 9)
  - McDougal, M.S. (2 folders), 1954-1987 (Box 9)
  - Mexico, 1986 (Box 9)
  - N, 1980-1987 (Box 9)
  - New York Law School, 1982-1987 (Box 9)
  - O, 1980-1987 (Box 9)
  - P, 1983-1987 (Box 9)
  - R (2 folders), 1983-1987 (Box 10)
  - S (2 folders), 1983-1987 (Box 10)
  - T, 1983-1987 (Box 10)
  - TIAA, 1983-1987 (Box 10)
  - Turner, Robert, 1983-1987 (Box 10)
  - U, 1982-1985 (Box 10)
  - V, 1983-1986 (Box 10)
  - W (2 folders), 1981-1987 (Box 10)
  - Y-Z, 1984-1987 (Box 10)
  - Filing folder (Box 10)
  - Writings
    - "The Foreign Sovereign Immunities Act of 1976: Some Suggested Ammendments," by Myres S. McDougal and Robin Eve Jasper, undated (Box 10)
- Additional Material, 1930s-1960s; Accession 1995-M-002; 72; 72 boxes
  Addition inventory by Nancy Lyon and Carol King 1994 Aug
  Received from: Mures S. McDougal, 1994 Jul 12, Aug 9
  The material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
  General
  Photographs in box 12 were reported missing in 2014.
  - Correspondence/subject files
    - A-B (Box 1)
    - C-D (Box 2)
    - E-Hector (Box 3)
    - Higgins-K (Box 4)
    - L-Min (Box 5)
    - Mis-Ray (Box 6)
    - Re-So (Box 7)
    - Sox-Z (Box 8)
  - Notecards (Box 9–18)
  - Course materials (Box 19–22)
  - Association of American Law Schools (AALS) (Box 23–24)
  - AALS: International Court of Justice (ICJ); Fund for Peace; Atterbury, B. P. (Box 25–27)
  - Correspondence (Box 28–29)
  - Family correspondence (Box 30–31)
  - Correspondence, Aramco: materials related to arbitration between the Royal Government of Saudi Arabia and the Arabian American Oil Company (1956) (Box 32)
  - Aramco files (Box 33–35)
  - Aramco files; course material; student papers (Box 36–37)
  - Course material (Box 38–39)
  - Course material; student papers (Box 40–41)
  - Correspondence (Box 42–43)
  - Notecards; student papers (Box 44)
  - Notes (Box 45–50)
  - Correspondence
    - A-B (Box 51)
    - C-Evans (Box 52)
    - P-H (Box 53)
    - I-L (Box 54)
    - M-0; unsorted folders (Box 55)
    - P-S (Box 56)
    - S (cont'd)-W (Box 57)
    - XYZ; subject files (Box 58)
  - Property files (Box 59)
  - Property files; unidentified subject files (Box 60)
  - Unidentified subject files (Box 61–65)
  - Unidentified subject files: social insurance materials (Box 66)
  - Social insurance materials (Box 67)
  - Social insurance materials: property files (Box 68)
  - Property files (Box 69–70)
  - Unidentified subject files (Box 71–72)
- Additional Material, Mid 1950s-late 1980s; Accession 1995-M-082; 8; 8 boxes
  Addition inventory by Nancy Lyon and Carol King 1995 Feb
  Received from: Myres S. McDougal, 1994 Nov 16
  - Correspondence/subject files
    - General, with law schools, mid 1950s-early 1960s, mid 1970s-1988 (Box 1)
    - Résumés, recommendations for teaching posts, fellowships
      - A-L, Late 1950s (Box 2)
      - M-U, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Aegean Sea Continental Shelf Case, 1973-1976 (Box 3–4)
    - Resumes (W-Z) (Box 4–5)
    - Law, Science and Policy Decision Seminars, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Security clearance/procedures re: classified information, 1960s (Box 5)
    - Industrial security (Box 5)
    - American Society of International Law, late 1950s (Box 6)
    - Subject files, notes on various cases (Box 6)
    - Publishing files, book reviews (Box 7)
    - Unsorted files (Box 7)
    - King-Seely Thermos Co., 1970s (Box 8)
    - Additional correspondence, résumés, unsorted materials, 1950s (Box 8)
- Additional Material, 1922-(1950s-1980s)-1994; Accession 1995-M-212
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site. Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Correspondence [with scattered printed material], 1930s-(1950s-1980s)-1994, undated (Box 1–6)
  - Notecards, undated (Box 7–11)
  - Audio cassettes and tapes
    - Lasswell, Harold [memorial service], 1979 April 7 (Box 12)
    - "Nicaraqua v. U.S.", 1984 October 16
      - McDougal Pleading in Nicaragua v. United States, a (Box 12)
      - McDougal oral arguments, 2 (Box 12)
      - Mother tape 12 (Box 12A)
      - Mother tape 13 (Box 12B)
    - "Doctrine of Precedent," [n.y.], March 24 (Box 12)
    - "McDougal's Jurisprudence: Utility, Influence, Controversy,", undated (Box 12)
    - Philippine Mission to the United Nations, undated (Box 12)
    - Unidentified, blank, undated (Box 12)
  - Plaques
    - World Community Association, 1959 (Box 12)
    - New York Law School Alumni, 1981 (Box 12)
    - Harold D. Lasswell Award, 1983 (Box 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1930s-1950s
    - Photographs, 1994, undated (Box 12)
    - Speeches by and about M. S. McDougal, 1985, undated (Box 12)
    - Color reproductions of portrait of M. S. McDougal, undated (Box 12)
      see also: Folio
  - Oversized items - folio
    - High school diploma, 1922 (Folder 13)
    - University of Mississippi [B.A., M.A.], 1926, 1927 (Folder 13)
    - University of Oxford [Bachelor of Civil Law], 1930 (Folder 13)
    - Yale University [J.S.D.], 1931 (Folder 13)
    - Great Navy of the Sovereign State of Oklahoma [commission as admiral], 1963 (Folder 13)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences [induction as Fellow], 1972 (Folder 13)
    - Color reproduction of portrait of M. S. McDougal, undated (Folder 13)
    - College of John the Baptist [sketch], 1981 (Box 14)
- Additional Material, 1947-(1960s-1993); Accession 1996-M-031
  - Correspondence
    - [Pertaining to the Class of 1927, University of Mississippi], 1983-1992 (Box 1)
    - [Primarily professional; photographs interspersed], 1947-1993 (Box 1)
  - Audio cassettes
    - Commons Dinner, n.y., October 24 (Box 1)
    - Combined Luncheon with the Canadian Council on International Law, undated (Box 1)
    - Kelso, Elise, undated (Box 1)
    - "McDougal's Jurisprudence: Utility, Influence, Controversy", undated (Box 1)
    - Thirty-Third Annual Benjamin N. Cardozo Lecture, 1977 October 13 (Box 1)
    - [Interpreting, Supplementing, Integrating-Constitutive Process?], n.y. March 17 (Box 1)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 1)
  - Audio tapes
    - Law of Outer Space, undated (Box 1)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1997-M-118
  - Correspondence, subject files, course materials, notes, writings, and printed material, Circa 1950s-1980s (Box 1–26)
- Additional Material, Accession 1998-M-114
  - Correspondence, Circa 1988-1993
    - A-H (Box 1)
    - I-Q (Box 2)
    - R-Z (Box 3)
  - Christmas cards (Box 3–4)
  - Photographs/negatives, videotape, genealogical materials (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, teaching files, and printed material, 1929-1989 (Box 5–8)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-056
  Photographs in box 2 were reported missing in 2014.
  - Correspondence, 1986-1998
    - A-Z (Box 1)
  - Subject files
    - Birthday [eightieth], 1986 (Box 1)
    - Cordell Hull Award, Cumberland School of Law, Birmingham, Alabama, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Institut de Droit International, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Libya, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
    - Medal of Merit [Yale Law School], 1992 (Box 2)
    - Myres McDougal Fellowship, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Oral history project, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
    - Rhodes Scholarship Trust, 1994 (Box 2)
    - University of Mississippi [Lifetime Achievement Award, reunion weekend], 1996 March (Box 2)
    - University of the Philippines [honorary degree], 1994 (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - "The General Principles of the Law of War,", undated (Box 2)
  - Unsorted correspondence, printed material [6 folders]
  - Photograph albums
    - Birthday celebrations, conferences, University of Mississippi reunion, 1996 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-065
  - Memorial service in honor of Myres S. McDougal, Yale Law School, Levinson Auditorium [2 copies], 1998 October 4; 2 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-063
  - Correspondence, remembrances, guest register, and photographs from the memorial service for Myres S. McDougal, 1998 October 4 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-077
  - Correspondence/memorial tributes, 1998
    - A-H (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - J-M (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - N-Z (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Myres S. McDougal: Appreciations of an Extraordinary Man [a book of memorial essays and personal reflections by colleagues and friends], 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)